<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-08-25T18:34:30-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Michael Gagujas</title><subtitle>Software Engineer &amp; Android Developer</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Professional Self-Assessment</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/content/2024/08/17/self-assessment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Professional Self-Assessment" /><published>2024-08-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/content/2024/08/17/self-assessment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/content/2024/08/17/self-assessment/"><![CDATA[<p>As a student in SNHU’s Computer Science Program, my academic journey has been both a challenging and rewarding experience as I’ve delved into complex topics such as computer graphics, machine learning, and various forms of data structures. They’ve highlighted the importance of understanding tradeoffs and making informed decisions based on the efficiency, performance, and practicality of differing computational solutions. However, understanding and knowing solutions is not enough. The Software Development Lifecycle and its numerous methodologies have strongly emphasized the importance of understanding project requirements and being able to communicate with stakeholders to understand their needs.</p>

<p>During my time at SNHU, I have acquired a broad range of skills that have refined my foundational coding abilities and deepened my understanding of computer science principles. I’ve learned how to control numerous peripherals like Inter-Integrated Circuits (I2Cs), General Purpose Inputs/Outputs, and Universal Asynchronous Receivers/Transmitters in embedded systems, and I’ve deconstructed assembly language to understand the underlying operations of a computer system. In addition, numerous classes involving software security, secure coding, and software testing have strongly reinforced the importance of creating robust and secure software systems to maintain the confidentiality, integrity, and availability of data. But more importantly, SNHU has taught me how important effective communication, active listening, and fostering a sense of community within a team can be. I’ve been lucky to have collaborated with strong mentors and like-minded individuals who have challenged and inspired me to push my boundaries and think outside the box. Especially with how dynamic and rapid the computer science field can be, collaborating in various teams and environments has been an insightful and essential part of my learning process. Each team member brings unique skills and perspectives to the table, and being able to leverage these diverse strengths can lead to innovative solutions that may not have been individually possible. This diversity has broadened my understanding of different problem-solving techniques, and it has taught me that soft skills are just as important as technical skills in achieving project goals.</p>

<p>After participating in numerous classes and projects, one of my greatest strengths is my ability to break complex problems down into smaller tasks and find efficient ways to solve them systematically. This ability has been particularly useful in the field of computer graphics where matrix translations, rotations, and scaling operations can be intricate with low tolerance for errors. In actuality, it is something that drives my passion for Computer Science because coding is not just about being at a computer. It involves strong problem-solving skills, being able to critically think through complex scenarios, and using creativity to come up with innovative solutions. Especially as technology is rapidly evolving and the world continues to be heavily influenced by it, new challenges and opportunities are going to come forward, and I am eager to meet them head on. Just like with my Open Graphics Library project, which I will discuss later on, there’s so much potential to learn, improve, research, and discover. As dentists are using computer graphics to simulate surgeries, architects to visualize designs, and game developers to create immersive experiences, my interests in computer graphics have significantly spiked, and I hope to expand on the concepts that I’ve learn at SNHU by expanding my skillsets to other graphics libraries like DirectX and Vulkan.</p>

<p>Continuous learning is now a part of my lifestyle, and I relish waking up to new findings in emerging trends like generative AI, machine learning, and robotics because they are not only reshaping computer science. They’re transforming almost every industry and creating opportunities for innovation that people thought were previously unimaginable. However, they’re also raising concerns involving ethical and moral implications because of situations like deep fakes, algorithmic bias, and privacy invasion. Technology simplifies complex tasks, empowers individuals to do more, and drives innovation across various sectors, but it becomes meaningless if it’s misused and not accessible to everyone. As an aspiring software engineer, my goals are to use my skills and knowledge to further the software engineering profession and to continue technology’s positive impact on society.</p>

<p>For my current portfolio, I have two artifacts displayed, which are an Open Graphics Library project and an Android Studio Event Tracking App. For my Open Graphics Library project, it was created in March of 2024, and its purpose was to demonstrate my proficiency in generating accurate representations of three-dimensional objects and creating interactive graphics applications that respond to input devices like a keyboard, controller, and mouse. By understanding the complex algorithms needed to reconstruct a variety of shapes, especially complex ones like spheres, cylinders, and tori, I was able to successfully transform a 2D image into a realistic 3D scene with the help of textures, the Phong Lighting Model, and a strong understanding of the graphics pipeline. With textures, I was able to manipulate its application in different sequences and apply various effects to enhance the realism of the 3D scene.  The Phone Lighting Model, which involved managing ambient, diffuse, and specular light, was also instrumental in creating a realistic lighting effect for the scene. By carefully adjusting these three components and using various forms of light like a spotlight, point light, and direct light, I was able to simulate the way light interacts with objects in the scene, which created shadows, highlights, and color variations that added depth and realism to the 3D objects. Moreover, by using different forms of algorithms to perform matrix translations, scaling, and rotations, I was able to control the position, size, and orientation of the objects in my 3D scene. In conclusion, this project not only enhanced my problem-solving skills, but also deepened my understanding of software engineering and design principles.</p>

<p>For my second artifact, it was created in April of 2024 and was part of the final project for my Mobile Architecture and Programming class. The project involved building a fully functional mobile application that allowed a user to create an account, add events to a database, and after receiving user permission, could send SMS messaging notifications. The application was built in Android Studio and initially utilized SQLite to read and write data like user credentials and event information, but I’ve enhanced the project and used Firebase Realtime Database to store and sync data in real-time. This allowed users to have a more seamless user experience, since any changes could be instantly reflected across all devices. In addition, security was significantly enhanced by applying Google’s Firebase Authentication to allow users to authenticate with their emails and password. This not only improved the security of the application with secure transmission and storage of data but also provided a more personalized user experience. Overall, the project allowed me to delve deeper into the intricacies of mobile application development and understand the importance of user-centric design and security in software engineering.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="content" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a student in SNHU’s Computer Science Program, my academic journey has been both a challenging and rewarding experience as I’ve delved into complex topics such as computer graphics, machine learning, and various forms of data structures. They’ve highlighted the importance of understanding tradeoffs and making informed decisions based on the efficiency, performance, and practicality of differing computational solutions. However, understanding and knowing solutions is not enough. The Software Development Lifecycle and its numerous methodologies have strongly emphasized the importance of understanding project requirements and being able to communicate with stakeholders to understand their needs. During my time at SNHU, I have acquired a broad range of skills that have refined my foundational coding abilities and deepened my understanding of computer science principles. I’ve learned how to control numerous peripherals like Inter-Integrated Circuits (I2Cs), General Purpose Inputs/Outputs, and Universal Asynchronous Receivers/Transmitters in embedded systems, and I’ve deconstructed assembly language to understand the underlying operations of a computer system. In addition, numerous classes involving software security, secure coding, and software testing have strongly reinforced the importance of creating robust and secure software systems to maintain the confidentiality, integrity, and availability of data. But more importantly, SNHU has taught me how important effective communication, active listening, and fostering a sense of community within a team can be. I’ve been lucky to have collaborated with strong mentors and like-minded individuals who have challenged and inspired me to push my boundaries and think outside the box. Especially with how dynamic and rapid the computer science field can be, collaborating in various teams and environments has been an insightful and essential part of my learning process. Each team member brings unique skills and perspectives to the table, and being able to leverage these diverse strengths can lead to innovative solutions that may not have been individually possible. This diversity has broadened my understanding of different problem-solving techniques, and it has taught me that soft skills are just as important as technical skills in achieving project goals. After participating in numerous classes and projects, one of my greatest strengths is my ability to break complex problems down into smaller tasks and find efficient ways to solve them systematically. This ability has been particularly useful in the field of computer graphics where matrix translations, rotations, and scaling operations can be intricate with low tolerance for errors. In actuality, it is something that drives my passion for Computer Science because coding is not just about being at a computer. It involves strong problem-solving skills, being able to critically think through complex scenarios, and using creativity to come up with innovative solutions. Especially as technology is rapidly evolving and the world continues to be heavily influenced by it, new challenges and opportunities are going to come forward, and I am eager to meet them head on. Just like with my Open Graphics Library project, which I will discuss later on, there’s so much potential to learn, improve, research, and discover. As dentists are using computer graphics to simulate surgeries, architects to visualize designs, and game developers to create immersive experiences, my interests in computer graphics have significantly spiked, and I hope to expand on the concepts that I’ve learn at SNHU by expanding my skillsets to other graphics libraries like DirectX and Vulkan. Continuous learning is now a part of my lifestyle, and I relish waking up to new findings in emerging trends like generative AI, machine learning, and robotics because they are not only reshaping computer science. They’re transforming almost every industry and creating opportunities for innovation that people thought were previously unimaginable. However, they’re also raising concerns involving ethical and moral implications because of situations like deep fakes, algorithmic bias, and privacy invasion. Technology simplifies complex tasks, empowers individuals to do more, and drives innovation across various sectors, but it becomes meaningless if it’s misused and not accessible to everyone. As an aspiring software engineer, my goals are to use my skills and knowledge to further the software engineering profession and to continue technology’s positive impact on society. For my current portfolio, I have two artifacts displayed, which are an Open Graphics Library project and an Android Studio Event Tracking App. For my Open Graphics Library project, it was created in March of 2024, and its purpose was to demonstrate my proficiency in generating accurate representations of three-dimensional objects and creating interactive graphics applications that respond to input devices like a keyboard, controller, and mouse. By understanding the complex algorithms needed to reconstruct a variety of shapes, especially complex ones like spheres, cylinders, and tori, I was able to successfully transform a 2D image into a realistic 3D scene with the help of textures, the Phong Lighting Model, and a strong understanding of the graphics pipeline. With textures, I was able to manipulate its application in different sequences and apply various effects to enhance the realism of the 3D scene. The Phone Lighting Model, which involved managing ambient, diffuse, and specular light, was also instrumental in creating a realistic lighting effect for the scene. By carefully adjusting these three components and using various forms of light like a spotlight, point light, and direct light, I was able to simulate the way light interacts with objects in the scene, which created shadows, highlights, and color variations that added depth and realism to the 3D objects. Moreover, by using different forms of algorithms to perform matrix translations, scaling, and rotations, I was able to control the position, size, and orientation of the objects in my 3D scene. In conclusion, this project not only enhanced my problem-solving skills, but also deepened my understanding of software engineering and design principles. For my second artifact, it was created in April of 2024 and was part of the final project for my Mobile Architecture and Programming class. The project involved building a fully functional mobile application that allowed a user to create an account, add events to a database, and after receiving user permission, could send SMS messaging notifications. The application was built in Android Studio and initially utilized SQLite to read and write data like user credentials and event information, but I’ve enhanced the project and used Firebase Realtime Database to store and sync data in real-time. This allowed users to have a more seamless user experience, since any changes could be instantly reflected across all devices. In addition, security was significantly enhanced by applying Google’s Firebase Authentication to allow users to authenticate with their emails and password. This not only improved the security of the application with secure transmission and storage of data but also provided a more personalized user experience. Overall, the project allowed me to delve deeper into the intricacies of mobile application development and understand the importance of user-centric design and security in software engineering.]]></summary></entry></feed>